<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-05-08T11:58:39-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Lenny’s VIS Thesis</title><subtitle>The journal+sketchbook for my Newhouse VIS thesis project.</subtitle><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Thesis 28: slow and disoriented</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/07/thesis-28.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 28: slow and disoriented" /><published>2019-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-07T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/07/thesis-28</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/07/thesis-28.html">&lt;p&gt;I was working on some revisions to my proposal today, but in between doing errands with mom and dad, I ended up not doing a lot of actual work. I read through the secret Aerodynamicist’s BBC column and watched a lot of videos explaining different F1 concepts. Tomorrow I’ll finish the revised proposal, send it out, and move on to gathering info on all the cars I want to use. Or at least that’s the plan. I’ve been feeling very disoriented and slightly annoyed today.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">I was working on some revisions to my proposal today, but in between doing errands with mom and dad, I ended up not doing a lot of actual work. I read through the secret Aerodynamicist’s BBC column and watched a lot of videos explaining different F1 concepts. Tomorrow I’ll finish the revised proposal, send it out, and move on to gathering info on all the cars I want to use. Or at least that’s the plan. I’ve been feeling very disoriented and slightly annoyed today.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 27: good morning so far</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/06/thesis-27.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 27: good morning so far" /><published>2019-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/06/thesis-27</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/06/thesis-27.html">&lt;p&gt;Had a good chat with Upton about both my master’s project, and the data journalism class in the fall. I’ll be updating my proposal to identify the direction I’m moving in and then in the evening I’ll return to Bjarni’s thesis and give feedback on a chapter. I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://benfry.com/phd/dissertation/3.html&quot;&gt;chapter three&lt;/a&gt; of Ben Fry’s PhD presentation, &lt;a href=&quot;https://benfry.com/phd/dissertation/&quot;&gt;Computational Information Design&lt;/a&gt;, and found it a good background on all the components that can come together to give form to data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Had a good chat with Upton about both my master’s project, and the data journalism class in the fall. I’ll be updating my proposal to identify the direction I’m moving in and then in the evening I’ll return to Bjarni’s thesis and give feedback on a chapter. I read chapter three of Ben Fry’s PhD presentation, Computational Information Design, and found it a good background on all the components that can come together to give form to data.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 26: No work on Saturday</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/04/thesis-26.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 26: No work on Saturday" /><published>2019-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/04/thesis-26</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/04/thesis-26.html">&lt;p&gt;Did nothing related to my thesis today except tidy up all the papers I had lying around my desk + shelf and open my proposal and highlight the parts I want to update. I ran errands today and felt slow, lethargic even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still thinking about what’s after and I’m excited to apply to CSE programs. The top schools for Computational Science and Engineering programs (ranked by &lt;a href=&quot;https://cwur.org/2017/subjects.php#Mathematics,%20Interdisciplinary%20Applications&quot;&gt;CWUR&lt;/a&gt;) are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;USA&lt;/em&gt; University of Texas at Austin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;USA&lt;/em&gt; Stanford University&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;USA&lt;/em&gt; Northwestern University&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spain&lt;/em&gt; Polytechnic University of Catalonia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;USA&lt;/em&gt; University of Illinois at Urbana–Champaign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;China&lt;/em&gt; Dalian University of Technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;USA&lt;/em&gt; University of California, San Diego&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;USA&lt;/em&gt; Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Singapore&lt;/em&gt; National University of Singapore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Germany&lt;/em&gt; Technical University of Munich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these, I’m interested in UT Austin because Prof. Wilcox is there, Poytechnic University of Catalonia (UPC in Catalan/spanish), and TU Münich. MIT is interesting too, but I kind of don’t want to go there for grad school. I spent two summers in a robotics lab at UPC and I enjoyed it, so it would be nice. Münich would also be nice, I had spotted their program when looking at product design masters. It’s taught in english which is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for now, I focus on my thesis + my upcoming course at UM. And finding a second job/internship for the fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At night I think I should spend ~2–3 hours reviewing past coursework. Something I talked about with Bjarni, but something I haven’t really started. I was thinking of starting with 18.02 and 8.01 and moving from there. He did something similar while studying for quals and said he wished he had done it earlier. I figure it works because after dinner I usually dick around and get very little done. If I channel that time to reviewing old lessons it could be a slow progress to reviewing my undergrad ahead of more technical work I want to engage in the future. Visualization is a part of it, but I do wish I could do more computational work. I did enjoy the research of that first summer at UPC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still dread learning JS. I’m doing it via D3 and I think I found a good book for JS, &lt;a href=&quot;http://eloquentjavascript.net/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eloquent Javascript&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, but we’ll see about the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I’m going to dad’s for lunch which should be… interesting in an interesting way. I’ll take a book with me (Maybe the truthful art, maybe minsky).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Did nothing related to my thesis today except tidy up all the papers I had lying around my desk + shelf and open my proposal and highlight the parts I want to update. I ran errands today and felt slow, lethargic even.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 25: Slow Progress is still Progress.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/03/thesis-25.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 25: Slow Progress is still Progress." /><published>2019-05-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/03/thesis-25</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/03/thesis-25.html">&lt;p&gt;The day really flew by. I worked on my D3 prototype of the driver standings and ended the day with these three iterations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lennymartinez.com/vis-thesis/prototype/line-chart-senna.html&quot;&gt;Senna’s career&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lennymartinez.com/vis-thesis/prototype/line-chart-1991.html&quot;&gt;The 1991 Season&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lennymartinez.com/vis-thesis/prototype/line-chart-all.html&quot;&gt;All the races&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having all 840+ drivers is too much. But making this prototype was helpful. For this direction, I’ll move to create a list of the winners + their teammates for every season and plot this smaller subset of careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lennymartinezd/status/1124352049183903745&quot;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; about my progress today, and how I got to the end. I’m quite happy I made such a big mess at the end, because I have a point from which I can move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the other direction, I should start gathering the list of all the cars I want to feature and at least make illustrations of the ones I have available (1950–2004). I’ll work on my proposal tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started watching Anthony Bourdain’s show again. I was at the start of the ninth season. Watching it reminded me of the visualization I wanted to do by looking at all the places, people, topics, and food that were involved in the show. There might be some interesting connections and commonalities across the episodes (not counting Anthony being in them).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">The day really flew by. I worked on my D3 prototype of the driver standings and ended the day with these three iterations:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 24: Connecting the dots</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/02/thesis-24.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 24: Connecting the dots" /><published>2019-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/02/thesis-24</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/02/thesis-24.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I finished putting together a master results table that has info on the races, the drivers, and the constructors. I made a few slices to test with: the 1991 season and Senna’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While getting the car maintained I ran into these two pieces from fivethirtyeight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-best-formula-one-driver-might-be-a-guy-who-hasnt-won-since-2013/&quot;&gt;The Best Formula One Driver Might Be A Guy Who Hasn’t Won Since 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/formula-one-racing/&quot;&gt;Who’s The Best Formula One Driver Of All Time?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They made me panic because I thought the analyses were much better than what I could produce. But then I talked things through with Ron and myself and decided to focus on making 1 good piece. Ron said to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lenny make the kind of stuff you want to see yourself making in the future.&lt;br /&gt;
Please don’t worry what will work and what won’t&lt;br /&gt;
if you find something cool and exciting, chances are others might dig it too&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While talking to Ron the thing that came to mind most vividly was the realization I had during AP World History and AP European History, that though our books were chaptered, history itself was happening simultaneously and we were going back and forth in time in this web of interconnected events. I want to make something like that with Formula 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ll work on a single project and make it a good one. I couldn’t decide whether it would better to make the timeline using cars as the unit of progress/time or using the races and the drivers. I’ll be doing some small prototypes of both and then deciding on which one seems better. I think the information and some of the graphics will be transferable regardless of the direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be updating my proposal this weekend. I’m talking with Jodi on Monday. Tomorrow I’m also talking with a creative director about an internship in industrial design/product design in south florida. I’m still excited by that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow I’ll be working on my timeline prototype with Senna’s data. I want to write my ten-year essay over the weekend or tomorrow night. I think I’m moving towards clarity, but we’ll see at the end of this process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Today I finished putting together a master results table that has info on the races, the drivers, and the constructors. I made a few slices to test with: the 1991 season and Senna’s career.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 23: Senna</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/01/thesis-23.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 23: Senna" /><published>2019-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/01/thesis-23</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/05/01/thesis-23.html">&lt;p&gt;This morning I watched the documentary, Senna, that was on Netflix. I thought the whole thing was very well made with the archival footage and the different angles. I was surprised by his strong faith which doesn’t seem as noticeable today. I would watch it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I worked on cleaning and putting together my master results list to start doing the counting. I got as far as adding the driver info the results table. Tomorrow I’ll add the constructor and the race information. I found this whole website just now: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statsf1.com/en/default.aspx&quot;&gt;https://www.statsf1.com/en/default.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be very useful as I check the data I have and look up information about the drivers and the cars. I’m still thinking about what the third chapter of the project will be: racetracks or an annotated timeline. Going with racetracks gives the story it’s third leg, because you already have the drivers and the cars. Making the annotated timeline would also be interesting because it’s about the intersection of the three legs: &lt;strong&gt;drivers&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;cars&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;racetracks&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;check in with AC guys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;get car oil changed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;return things at home depot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;finish making master results table&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create line charts of 1991 season&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Chapter 12 of IDVFTW (I need to finish the book by next Wednesday)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While getting the car maintained, I’ll be reading more of the truthful art. Now I’m off to read the intro + first chapter of Eloquent Javascript. While working on my master’s I want to further imrpove my JS knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">This morning I watched the documentary, Senna, that was on Netflix. I thought the whole thing was very well made with the archival footage and the different angles. I was surprised by his strong faith which doesn’t seem as noticeable today. I would watch it again.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 22: Drivers, Cars, Racetracks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/30/thesis-22.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 22: Drivers, Cars, Racetracks" /><published>2019-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-30T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/30/thesis-22</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/30/thesis-22.html">&lt;p&gt;Today I went through the tutorial, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstpythonnotebook.org/&quot;&gt;First Python Notebook&lt;/a&gt;, and got acquainted more with the kind of manipulations I can do with pandas. I had moved my journal to a separate repo yesterday, so I took this tutorial today to start reviewing my data cleaning/wrangling and work to get the data I want for the driver comparisons set up. My goal is to get that set up and isolate the 2018 races and get something working with Hamilton and Bottas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spoke with Bjarni this evening and he suggested complimenting the cars + driver chapters, with one on the racetracks and trying to find the best formula one track. I had been thinking of racetracks before I thought to do a visual history of the tracks, but maybe there’s something we can do with the tracks, looking at changes, seasons they were used, fatalities, races where everyone finished, or something along those lines. I need to look at the data more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also started creating a draft syllabus template to start working on my journalism class. These two projects + the books I want to read should keep me occupied for the next three and a half months.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Today I went through the tutorial, First Python Notebook, and got acquainted more with the kind of manipulations I can do with pandas. I had moved my journal to a separate repo yesterday, so I took this tutorial today to start reviewing my data cleaning/wrangling and work to get the data I want for the driver comparisons set up. My goal is to get that set up and isolate the 2018 races and get something working with Hamilton and Bottas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 21: 100 Days and a new, new direction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/29/thesis-21.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 21: 100 Days and a new, new direction" /><published>2019-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/29/thesis-21</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/29/thesis-21.html">&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend I got feedback from Alberto on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/16LbWha2qk56mawVR8bYwsTJMAWMQ6hOihMLpJwbu0o0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why three projects? Just one is more than enough work for three months, I can assure you, if you want to design something that, say, is worth publishing by The Pudding. I’d prefer to have a very strong, deep, well-designed project rather than three merely OK ones.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about it for the longer part of the day and whined a little and ended up writing to Mike about re-focusing my efforts into making something worth publishing by The Pudding. So I’m looking back to gather my thoughts and move forward to prototyping the angles I have so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have 100 days until the defense, and I think I can get further and more focused if I were to treat this like a proper design project. I’ve had some time to look at the data and ideate directions (listed bellow). I’ll review them and pick 3 to explore and make prototypes for. Each prototype should help me answer a question that I’m most worried about with each idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All ideas I’ve had related to Formula 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a visual history of the cars (an analogue to The Pudding’s piece piece on Air Jordan sneakers), looking at every championship driver’s car, as well as the cars that appeared in one-off races. The goal being to chart the evolution of F1 cars from 1950 to present, providing seasoned fans of the sports opportunities to find new information and to provide an introduction to the sport via the cars to a newbie fan. Maybe a visual history of the cars noting the really interesting ones and why they’re interesting in the same style as the Pudding piece, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pudding.cool/2018/09/jordans/&quot;&gt;A visual history of every Air Jordan&lt;/a&gt;. I can see myself cutting the car up into modules and transitioning each piece during the move forward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at the championship drivers and try to find who the best drivers from this subset have been. For this idea I wanted to focus on seeing how dominating they were in their season and how they compared to their teammate who drove the same car.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating an annotated timeline of the sport where each race was on the x-axis and the y-axis was the standings at each race. I’d then add annotations to notable events during each race (final races, fatal crashes, special cars debuting, championship securing race).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a simulation where you pick two drivers and have them race on a variety of tracks to see who’s better.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;look at standings and figure out who’s the best driver in each category: most podiums; most championships; takes their constructor up the standings; races for a constructor who’s been previously successful in the championship; averages a high ending position over seasons; time series of positions over seasons; overtakes the most.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who have been the best drivers in the first 1000 races? I want to look at the history of the sport through the drivers and the races and the impactful events. I was thinking the main graphic element would be the slope diagram that charts the driver standings over the course of each season. Then I add annotations to special events that happen at each race. Some examples I’m thinking of are: clinches world title, fatality, announces retirement, first podium, retires from race due to mechanical damage, started in P-12 and ended in P4. I could then see who have been the really consistent drivers and who have been the best drivers: schumacher, senna, vettel, hamilton, etc. I could use this idea and snapshot it to talk about the best drivers, and then have a more interactive version of it at the bottom for people to play with. I don’t know yet how it would play out on mobile (maybe it’s vertical plots vs horizontal ones; or maybe it’s not even phone friendly).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how driver championship standings change over the course of the season (and how that has changed over the many seasons)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;visualizing all the races taking notes of fatalities, how many races per season, race location, race accidents, and which cars didn’t finish&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;knowing who all the drivers were, when they raced, and what kind of records they set.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;looking at how the set of constructors have changed and who has been the most successful constructor (both overall and if we were to normalize by how long they were in F1)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Figuring out the best driver, with different best definitions (most championships, podiums, consistency, most moves up from the grid)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looking at how often drivers switch racing teams and if that correlates with their performance (win in a small team, get a big team to pay you more?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to keep in mind projects I admire:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/billionaires/&quot;&gt;Bloomberg Billionaires Index&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pudding.cool/2018/09/jordans/&quot;&gt;A visual history of every Air Jordan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://rhythm-of-food.net/&quot;&gt;Rhythm of Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On 17 April, I wrote this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;From the pudding piece I think a similar approach could be applied to every driver (800+) or racetrack(~70). And within each driver’s description, more of their career and achievements could be shown/explained. If we focus on racetracks we could point out the history of the track, any fatalities/crashes, and other tidbits.&lt;br /&gt;
Using the Bloomberg Billionaires Index as a base, I’m inspired by the biggest movers in Formula 1, on both the sides of the constructors, and the side of the drivers. I want to see how the rankings for the drivers change over the course of each season. And I want to see how career lives of the constructors change: total points over their existence in F1.&lt;br /&gt;
From the Rhythm of Food I’m drawn to the seasonality aspect and the depth you can through the data. F1 is an annual sport so I think some aspect of Moritz’s piece can transfer to F1 data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll revisit this for inspiration: &lt;a href=&quot;https://visual.ly/tag/formula-1&quot;&gt;https://visual.ly/tag/formula-1&lt;/a&gt;. I can also keep these pages in mind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Formula_One_fatalities&quot;&gt;F1 fatalities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportschord.com/formula-1&quot;&gt;a visual history of F1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-new-direction&quot;&gt;New New Direction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I “pitched” three angles for Formula 1 stories visualizations to Alberto on Saturday:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A visual history of the cars&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An annotated timeline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Looking at the championship drivers to show who the best one is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard back from him this afternoon:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What about if you choose just one topic but you design those THREE big sections for it? That way it’d be equally challenging, but much more focused. And you’d have three portfolio pieces, but that could be published as a single very long story.&lt;br /&gt;
And you could pitch this to The Pudding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one way to reconcile things. I’ll have to update my proposal file, but we’ll have three chapters on Formula 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An analysis of the championship drivers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An annotated timeline of the first 1000 races&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A visual history of the cars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll be looking at this more closely this week, what each one would entail and keep working on the championship driver analysis. Ali made the good suggestion of setting the end of this week as a deadline for modifying my thesis further. I’ll be holding myself to this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Over the weekend I got feedback from Alberto on my proposal:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 19: Unproductive day</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/25/thesis-19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 19: Unproductive day" /><published>2019-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/25/thesis-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/25/thesis-19.html">&lt;p&gt;Went to bed late again last night reading comics. Took grandma to her appointment today and was really tired and unproductive for the day. I ran a few errands after lunch and I did read through some or most of nadieh’s projects with a focus on the sketching and some of the execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did a few of the observable tutorials, but I can’t seem to connect them to github so I don’t particularly think they’ll be as useful for what I want. I was looking for a way to combine notebooks + github to track my js work… There is a js kernel for jupyter that I may give a go, but I think working with a browser and vscode will probably be the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still thinking about circles for the F1 driver data, but want to maybe include a version of the graphs that allows for better comparison. Will sketch tomorrow (with colors pencils) and work to move forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to bed early to be more rested for tomorrow. Might read a bit more of lifelong kindergarten, but will not be reading manga or watching netflix until I finish my thesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IDVFTW chapter 11&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sketch ideas for F1 data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at the book of circles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Went to bed late again last night reading comics. Took grandma to her appointment today and was really tired and unproductive for the day. I ran a few errands after lunch and I did read through some or most of nadieh’s projects with a focus on the sketching and some of the execution.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thesis 18: Green light</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/24/thesis-18.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thesis 18: Green light" /><published>2019-04-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-04-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/24/thesis-18</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/vis-thesis-journal/2019/04/24/thesis-18.html">&lt;p&gt;Mike gave the green light on my proposal today, so I’m moving forward with that. I think I also landed a research assistant job for the summer looking at and for startups for a report. So that’s a part-time job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to go with the F1 data project related to finding the best driver. I went through the spreadsheets and re-organized the Ids to be more chronological. Drivers are organized by dob (Excel does not play well with dates before 1900), and races by chronological order. Everything else follows from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this data I’ll be looking mainly at the results data that has the end results (position/points) for each of the first 1000 races. I have the data all ready, so I’m moving to the sketching part of the project. I’m trying to balance cyclical nature of a season with comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also debating going back to R to do analysis and test visualizations because I used so little of pandas: making a dataframe, joining two dataframes. ggplot2 seems like a way to test things on a small-scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve started looking at observable tutorials as well which could prove a good way to prototype and build the final visualization, to a degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent the morning and part of the early afternoon with grandma who had cataract surgery today. She has another appointment early tomorrow in Miramar. So that’s going to be my morning tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at the book of circles for ideas on F1 dataviz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;IDVFTW chapter 11&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Figure out how to use observable notebooks within a repo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look through the data sketches projects to learn a little bit more about their sketching process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name>Lenny Martinez Dominguez</name><email>lennymartinezd@gmail.com</email></author><summary type="html">Mike gave the green light on my proposal today, so I’m moving forward with that. I think I also landed a research assistant job for the summer looking at and for startups for a report. So that’s a part-time job.</summary></entry></feed>